Where did
we stop?  343.
Yes,
[the music] is
good.   There's nothing
wrong with starting there.
Good.  Zin speaks to the lady.  Yes.  0 dollars.
She talks to them.
Incomprehension.
She speaks of ignorance.
By the way, I heard that you have finished your
idyll drawings,
and I heard that I will receive them from
each house tomorrow.  Yes.
And I heard you did great, but
I need to wait until tomorrow.  Yes,
she calls him ignorant.  Do you think
you should have spoken out against it?  You have
no strength, and that's not even what
creates your good qualities.
And now we will begin at verse 332.
I say that nothing depends on
nothing,
that everything depends on nothing.  For you,
things are immovable, unchanging, solid, and
unwavering.  In your worldview, nothing
can exist at all.
And therefore there is no hope.
Someone in the audience gave an indirect answer
.
Well, how do you know that things
are changing?
You get hungry after lunch, you sit in these
long classes and you get
hungrier, you think about food.
No one can say that things don't
change.  Ignorance does not mean that
things do not change.  He never
says that.  Why does she accuse him of
saying that?  It is
about an Angel accusing the
devil.  I taught cursive.  And if
a person
asks something, have you helped answer the
question yet?
Yes, I said.  So Ye is just waiting for
someone in the audience to answer.  So
listen.
If things didn't come from grains, they would
never change.  In your mind, you
think things come from there,
from the outside in.  100 dollars.  Who will say
that about you?
This didn't allow him to
rise.
In this country, you can win more than
anything, but that doesn't mean you'll become
president.
Who
said dance?
Anyone who thinks that everything is the same is mistaken
.  I don't know.  So when we say "
thrower"
and write in the chat,
it
means that what comes to us is
how you see things.  And what is an aria?
Arya means one who has touched the
diamond world directly.
And this opposite does not mean aria.  These are the ones who
think the world is like you.
They don't understand that the world comes from
you.
And that leads us to the next question.
What's wrong with my beer today?  I can't
.  I don't trust you.  Ready?  very
easy money.
If your family asks you why you
took a week to go to Mazna Gora,
you can say, "I'll get more
money there than I thought."  Did
you answer that?  How many times a
diamond keeper?
[music]
Uh, yeah.  Zero.  How many people remember the
diamond?  Zero.
Director
Yelse responded here.  She led for more than 20 years.
And what does "diamond" mean in Sanskrit?   In
Sanskrit it is vajra,
which
also means power.
Yes, it also means
vegetables.  So vajra is the root of the
English word vegetables.  In the old days
they would have agreed with my
wife.  They would say that vegetables
make you stronger.  And in ancient times,
they believed that vegetables were good for your
health, so they made you stronger.
Therefore, the ancient English word
vegetables
has the root vajera.  And every time
someone asks you about a diamond, you
can ask why they ask you that
, because now you are in a class
on the diamond path and you need to always
think about what message they want to
tell you.
This is the entrance to the diamond path.  This is your entrance to the
diamond path.  Does a diamond have any meaning to the
Diamond Cutter's Sutra?
And if you're in this class, if you're in a
really very diamond path class, then
you have to say, well, of course it makes sense.
So, how is
this possible and too much money, let's
answer it without money.
She accuses the devil of
believing that nothing
can ever change.  She
says you believe that nothing can
change.
Why?  Why does she say that?
Yes, give me a microphone, but not for
financial gain.
There are some people who have to pay
a teacher $100 to get the
right answer.
Okay, don't forget the question.  Why does the angel
accuse
[music] of a
wrong worldview?  She says
you think nothing changes.
Of course, he doesn't think so.  You and I, we have
not yet followed the diamond path, but
we believe that nothing can change.  We
see that things are changing every
moment.
She blames the devil.
She blames the devil because he
falls into one of the extremes.
If you think that things come from
your own side, then the result of that
belief is that
they do not change.  That's why you
[musicians]
say what you say.  If you
believe that things originate in this way, not
from you, if a thing exists from its own
side, it cannot change.  It would
not be able to change if it did not
come from your grains.
What grains?  Why do things change?  Your
grains are changing.
The seeds you planted.  They planted a tree, the
tree grew, and the grain ran out.
Grain gives energy to the tree.  A tree takes
energy, grows, and dies.  If things
come from your seeds, they must
die.  They are not permanent.  But if they
don't come from your seeds, why
should they change?  If that's not how it comes about,
then why should they change?  And so she
accuses him of,
well, you believe it.  Yes, that's right.
The devil says, "I didn't say that, but
you believe that. Is that what you say?"
Then he accuses her of not having any
friends.
He accuses her of not having any
He says she is lonely,
accuses
her of never coming home.  Where is the
mind?  In
our minds
for a year, when you are in classes on Diamond
Mountain, and the rest of the time where are you?  Other times you
wonder who is annoying you?  Do you understand?
The devil accuses Angel of having
no friends, of never even
coming home to her husband.  And
what does she say?
It's not that I don't have friends, it's that
you don't have friends.  Why?  Because you those
friends you think exist, they do
n't even exist.
Every time you
argue with your husband next time, you will start
fighting.  Think about it, remember it.
He will probably get even more confused.
So if things don't come from you, they can't
exist.  First, they cannot
change.  Second, they could not
exist at all.   Do
you know about the two men in the kitchen?
Yes.   a
man who hurts you even
if you didn't do anything.  There is no such thing.
I didn't do anything.
The one who parodies me when I
say that.  I didn't do anything.  I think
he uses it at home.  Don't tell
him, don't tell him.
The wife says,
"My husband just started yelling at me
. I didn't do anything."  And in this
system, if the pen comes from you, then
the man comes from you.  The man
said something to you, it comes from you.  Then you will be
upset.
If you understand where it comes from,
then you can change things.  If you don't
understand, then it doesn't exist.  This is the thing
that always exists.
Then he tells her, "You don't have any
friends."  And she replies:
"I'm friends with everyone, everyone is my friend."
Don't say that everyone, uh, that mine doesn't have any
friends.  After all, everyone in this world is my
friend.
And who says this?  Yes, a young man who
understands Zerpa.
And the people in the world, my friends, I love everyone
and they love me because I am
real.  I come from grains.  I have
real seeds that come from, oh,
real relationships that come from seeds.
When I start relationships,
I can have them because I respect the
relationships of others.  I don't shout, I don't argue
with my husband.  I respect, I keep my
promises.
And
I encourage others to keep
their vows and their promises.
And so, if you understand that things
come from grains, you can be closer to
everything, because it is the real, true,
one world.  Do you understand?  It's not like the
handle comes from the grain.  Everything comes from
grain.  If you don't understand this, then
you are not living in the real world, in a
world that doesn't exist.  Then you are not
crazy.  This means that 8 billion
people are like this or they will be.  I'm not
saying they won't.  I'm not saying
they will.
The next thing she says, she's an angel,
she's talking about the idea of ​​friendship.  And it
speaks to the idea that people are
naturally, they are friends, they are all
close to me.
Because they depend on me, just as the
world depends on me, my cheeses.
The world depends on me.  Don't tell me I do
n't have friends.  Or every
time your husband tells you that
you don't have friends, I have friends.  I have a
lot of friends because my mind
creates everything.
Now the $100 question.  Oh, everyone
woke up at once.
So he says,
"You're lonely, you have no friends. You
come home once a year. Your mind.
Yeah, when you go to the diamond mountain,
and you're all by yourself, you don't even have friends
."  And then she says:
"No, no, I have all my friends."  And he
says, "Why? I'm
all friends with me because they come
from me. Okay. The pen and everyone else
comes from me. That's why
they like [the music]. They're my friends.
See?
It's called dependent origination.
But there's a deeper idea. Do you want to hear it?
dependent origination, and I'll make it
easier for you.
The pen depends on your seeds.
Do you want it easier or really simple? Okay,
a little simple. The pen depends on your
seeds, so the pen is your friend.
Or you're a friend to the pen, because without you there would
n't be a friend of yours. See? It's
also your friend, the pen is your friend.
And
it's
interdependent origination.
Listen, I'll make it easier for you
. Yes, 100.
The tree depends on the seeds, and the seed
depends on the tree. So how is it that
the tree
grows and
how did the tree come
after the seed?
Yes, the seed makes the tree, but the tree
also makes the seed. You
can't just
$100. Okay.
Yes,
your seeds made the pen,
but the pen made the seeds.
Your grains made the pen, but the pen
made the grains so that you could see the pen. That's
real
interdependent
origination. Everybody says, "That's how it is
from me, I made this pen, made this
pen." But the pen created your grains
because there can't be grains until they
make something. See? That's
before the diamond path.
The pen is these grains, this is the diamond path. And
everyone else knows the secret.
Usually, usually with DCI students, everything
comes from you. Everything comes from you.
Grain, grain. Diamond path. Master,
master of one of the houses. The pen comes
from me
and the pen comes from my grains. New
wisdom.
And
I made the pen.
The pen comes from my grains.
And the grains exist because there is a pen. If
you think about it, interdependent
origination, it exists on both sides. And
it's much deeper. It's not usually
taught.
Yeah, $500. Wow, even Word. An
old example when we talk about
grains. What  the oldest example you
can give when we're talking
about grain in this case?
Spears spears
[music]
we're talking about this example.
In ancient times they didn't have handles, they had
these ash.
which was slippery.
It's a stick like this and
with a metal edge like this. They threw it into
war, used it.
And there's this agreement during ancient wars. They
say something like: "Let's take a break and
go to lunch." And everyone goes back to
their
sides, starts cooking and there
's not a single good warrior who would
put his spear on the ground, because they
know that's how he exercises, and so
they stack it up like this vertically
so that the metal particles stick
to each other, one to one to one. This
example and the handle, this example the handle
depends on the grain, and the grain depends on the
handle. This is a real interdependent
origin, you see? So this example
from the spear:
your husband comes from you, but you also
come from our husband.
And, by the way, when you have  something is difficult with
another person,
well, something is wrong,
you have
problems with him. And maybe
your problem is that you think that
person does not come from you, but maybe
he has problems too. He thinks that you do not
come from him either. So it works both
ways. And it is really true, because
the tree determines the grains,
if the other person with whom you have a bad
relationship, it is proof that you have a
bad relationship. And it is, well, difficult
to realize this reality. If someone
tells you that all idiots, then they come
from you, because they are a reflection of you. Well, that is
difficult to swallow
and it is according to you. But usually
too difficult.
Every time you say that I
want to study the Diamond Way, you say
that I do not want to study philosophy, I
just want to study the Diamond Way. And I have just
given you the Diamond Way.
So when she
argues, what is happening in this debate between
the angel and the devil, you need to
understand the mood of this debate.
The devil  says: "Angel, you come
home, you're always alone, you come once a year
.  I see you here once a year.  And
you spend
5 minutes thinking about how things are going when you
tell me about it.  Why should I
listen to you?  I am not alone.  Why should I
listen to you?  And she says, "I'm not
alone. You're alone. I'm with friends, with
everyone who lives on this planet, because
they're the tree and I'm the grain.
They made me who I am. It's very
profound.
There are people of the pen. Let's go back to DCI. Grain.
Grain. And the pen creates your grains.
Thank you. The pen. And the pen says, "Thank
you.  If it weren't for your grains, I would
n't be here.  But without you I wouldn't be able to
write.
I wouldn't have the balls to see it with a
pen.  Do you understand?  true
interdependent origins.
And here it works both ways in two
ways.
Here.  And that means she's not alone and
she knows it.  If you understand
addiction,
you are in a deep relationship with every
person on this planet.  And other planets,
but I'm not talking about that now.  Good?  I'll
say it again, if you really understand
the pen, then you,
if you understand the pen,
every person on this planet is
your friend.  You are dependent on each other.  Don't
say I'm lonely because I only
show up here once a year.  But I'm with
everyone and friends, but you're not.  He is not my
friend.  Do you understand why he is lonely?  Who is
he?  The devil, not poverty, is a misunderstanding of
this world, a wrong
worldview.
And then she talks about something
very attractive.  She is bragging.
You're a loser, you're lonely, you're always alone in your
head.  And I have friends, so many friends.
You don't even know how much.  And he asks something like this:
"Who's who? Who are your friends?"  And
she starts:
"And now here's a list of all my friends.
Sunrise,
moonrise
. The sun and the moon. My friends!
Cool! Yeah, directions, my friends.
and the West, they depend on me.
You see what that's about? She's bragging about
it. He accuses her of having no
friends, of being a loser, of having no one
. And she's a loser, I have friends in the
highest places. Where is the sun, the moon.
And I have sunrise and sunset.
I have day and night. They're my friends.
And also summer, winter, fall and spring, the
four seasons.
They're my friends.
And the fact that it rains
and that all the fruits ripen.
All of that comes from me. She keeps
bragging about how many friends she has.
All of my friends are $100 questions.
Can you buy another statue?
Oh, okay, he won't answer anything
terrible.
She's talking about borders.
She's saying that there's this division between
day and night,
sunrise and sunset. She  talks about the
boundaries between the seasons summer and winter. And
winter, yes, already answered in Sanskrit.
The topic,
it's 50 dollars.
And seven
as in Tibetan?
That is, two words that you have to learn
yourself
and the test am.
And in Tibetan, it's
long, such a
long speech seven in
English seven.
These, you see, these seams on the shirt,
this line, which is the sleeve, where they
united one part with another. And this
comes from the ancient Sanskrit sena and
sutra comes from this word as well. This is
this firoka, which is sewn.
Ima, which means boundaries, separation.
And this is very important for a retreat center.
For a retreat, this is very important for a
retreat center. Every time we
do a retreat, a serious retreat,
we do boundaries. We do two
boundaries.
Shila, how much, how much money will you give
for this question?
We do two boundaries at least.
We define two boundaries in the retreat. One
for what?
If someone runs up the mountain  and puts a
stick, it's called santo or you hang
mantras on the four sides of your house.
This is sima. What we call sima.
Say sima.
Care, the long pronunciation is like this. And it means
boundaries, separation. I say,
I spent three years, you remember, I was in the
car, I was finishing the book The
Diamond Cutter Sutra. The
last page, the translation. And we
come to the gate of our retreat
center. And I
gave Ellie my translation, the translation of
this book.
And I got out of the car, turned my
back,
closed
and closed the gate and said that I will not leave
this retreat for three years. And
it's a very strange feeling
when you stand there and say that you will
not leave this for three years, you will
not leave these boundaries. Free things
happened. I broke a tooth. It was bad.
another retreatant.
[music] I
had to go into town to
get my tooth fixed. And I  such that
let's just repair it, glue it
somehow. I just lost my tooth there
, yeah, that's all. Let's find it,
glue it with lei. And I didn't violate these
borders, I didn't violate them for years. I didn't
leave the reprint for years. And here is this
idea in the debate of the angel and the devil. The idea of
the seven. And what is the seven about here?
What is the separation between the pen and the grains, between
the sun and the moon, the sunrise and the sunset. Like
we used to have a project in Mexico
across the border. Well, Diamond Mountain is
not far from Mexico. If you climb
the mountain, you can see Mexico.
So when we say
across the border, it means that
the project was not far from Mexico. And I say, not
far from me. I literally came to
the border, started talking to the worker.
I told the police that I could
do something, and what did they do? They don't
trust you.
And
I say: "Just for fun, I want to
put  one foot in Mexico, and the other
foot in the States." I stood like this with two feet. I
stand, looking at this division, the
border between Mexico and the States. And,
you know, it feels the same. I do
n't feel anything. I don't feel any
border. I don't just see a desert,
some ford, dust. I don't see anything.
But this is a karmic line. There are a
lot of people on this side. They are
starving
and
only a little 2 m left-handed. And there they die from
overeating. That is, the hungry there
starve, and those on the side they die
from eating too much.
Your grains create this border. And this is what
the Angel says.
Borders of separation,
borders between you and others, borders between
your eyes and your pen.
separation between you and me. Separation
or borders. It all comes from the grain. It
all comes from your
grains. It doesn't just say: "You know,
the sun and the moon,
day and night and sunset come from  me.
She doesn't say that.  She says: "
You created the border."
By the way, if everyone understood this, then
we would have a capable language.  David and I agreed that
David could translate
from English to Chinese.  Then you
need to change all the languages, because these
languages ​​are based on a misunderstanding
.  You and I are a mistake.  And it's not that
if you're a good person, you have to
think of me as yourself.  No, that's
wrong.  There should be neither you nor
me.  We have to eat.  We should have
lunch.  It doesn't matter where the border is.  Do you understand what
I mean?  I am you, and you are me.  So if you
understand this,
and
the devil in your head says, "You
don't have any friends,
you don't understand that I have friends everywhere."
The angel says, "You're the loser, you're the loner,
you're the one who has no friends. You don't
understand, you can't understand, you can't
exist without other people.
You know? It's very, very powerful. And that's why it
took us 10 years to get to
this point. This verse alone, it's very
powerful. And when you think about it, wisdom
says understanding yourself, understanding the hand.
I have real friends, and you don't even
know what friends are. I have such
good friends that they are me. Don't say
I don't have friends.
The truth is
that I don't have friends. I am my friends.
That's how close we are. If you
understand that, your life is just incredible.
every day, every day is a holiday,
understanding that you are these people, a
holiday all day long, that doesn't stop,
you can joke, make jokes, laugh.
And it's fun,
fun.
Even all those things that he says,
if you want to enjoy every
day, think about that. And it's really
joyful.  And it's not just your
birthday, which happens once a year. What's the
deep wisdom here?
How many students do you have?
I say, 365. And each one has their own
mood. My wife says, "Don't eat
the coffee, don't eat the dessert." And I say, "
One of my students has a
birthday." So I can eat today,
celebrate a birthday. Each
of us has boundaries. They may not be
so obvious, but this applies
to retreats.
The word retreat in the ancient language of Ima and in
the Sanskrit of Samvetsk
means boundaries. It means to stay
within boundaries.
Sometimes you might think, "Well, there are no people
around you.  If you have a family, a
wife, you work, it's good to be with
other people, but sometimes it's good to be alone
in your retreat.
This is very wonderful.  You know, John Brady,
I have this thing.  I remember
looking out the window during my retreat and
saying,
"This is not cool. I remember
looking out the window during my retreat and
I looked out and said, "This is not cool.
I had no toilet, no electricity, no running
water. I was just stuck in the desert. I
said, "This is not cool.  Why?  Because there
was no one who could help me.
I can't enjoy, be happy
if I don't help someone else." I felt
lonely. Retreat is great, but I do
n't
even have a chance to prepare a cave for someone,
to say hello, to spend time. I don't have
time to serve others.
I think one of the reasons to
go on a retreat is, well, for example,
today it will be four days of retreat, a
silent retreat. I think you
will feel how you miss people and you
will miss people.
On the third day you will miss even
those who annoyed you. During this
silent retreat. This is the time when you
need to think about how to be a vidhisatva.
How to be a vidhisatva, when you are in a
deep retreat by yourself for a
long time, you will understand how much you
need other people, how cool and
sweet it is to live for others. And it doesn't matter whether
they are good people or not. Sometimes it's
even cooler to serve very
good people.
This is a real art. This is such an
advanced form of art  serve
bad people. How much time do they have?
Okay. And then
and then she says the
ingol
finally goes to another place.
Yes, verse 337, if someone has an open one.
And she says, are there
boundaries
between
the thieves of the year, spring, summer, winter, autumn,
winter. And then she says, "There are boundaries
between being alive and being dead."
And he says that there
is also another boundary.
She says, and it is called life and
death.
There are other divisions.
Maybe you are sick or in a train
. You may suffer in a
diamond mountain.
For example, in one week of
some
from some great heat. If you compare
the lack of a toilet and the heat, then I choose the
heat.
You have
a hearing,
that is, it goes to other boundaries.
She talks about how we age,
about the suffering of dying. And she says,
"I also created lines, these divisions
between the three truths.  I created
boundaries between
pain and the causes of pain, pain within pain.
I created four lines between the four
truths of the army, between life and death.
If you understand these lines, these
divisions, they come from you, you
can change it.  If you don't understand,
you can't change it.  Good?  If
you understand the seven, where the seven, this line
is divided, where it comes from, you can also
eliminate this seven between life and death.   Do
you understand?   A
Tatra lesson.  I'm telling you what I
want.
Sage, we are working on a special
project.  We help people figure out
what you will do in the second half of
your life.  We are developing one idea.  I
was teaching
it
and someone said to me: "So you're teaching the
second part of life? Yes, no, I'm
teaching the
first part here, and what happens after that?
And they're like, I don't
care that you're going to get
old, get sick, die. I'm
not interested in that. I'm teaching you
how you're going to move from this life to the
next,
how you're
going to do it artistically, beautifully. That's
what I'm teaching. This is the first part. The second
part, what happens after
you die? If you start a new
project, when you do it, it's the
first part of your new life,
then you become a master.
And this is the art of how to spend the second
part of your life. Don't think of
life
as the first half, the second half.
The second half is the first part of your
life. Do you understand?
And what happens after that? You die.
Then you have the second part of your life, the
second half. If you learn well,
do retreats and study the
diamond path, it's incredible. It's fun,
cool, incredible. That's great
super duper. Do you know what color the
sky will be in my next life?
Peach color. peach color
will be the sky in my next life.
Imagine,
you can
plant your next childhood or
adolescence.
Imagine, you can
sow those seeds now. You can say
either Heshela is crazy or he
knows something. But I don't care what you say,
if even you say I'm
crazy. I don't care if you
want to give $100,
okay, maybe I'm crazy, and maybe I
know something, that's a possibility that we can
say. Either he knows something, or he doesn't.
Right?
So I'm waiting for that. I'll
see you in the next world. Don't
be late.